Finding Aid for Julio Perazza visual materials, 1934-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Julio Perazza visual materials
1934-2004
Perazza, Julio.
6 linear feet in 7 boxes
2009180 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Ana Luisa Cardona (donor no. 10213 in two accessions: June 2009 and April 2014.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Julio Perazza was born in San Juan, Puerto Rico on August 29, 1943. After graduating from Western High School in Detroit, he studied at various places, including Highland Park Community College. He eventually completed his B.F.A. in photography at the University of Michigan (1975) and his M.F.A. in photography from Eastern Michigan University.
He worked for a time at Great Lakes Steel, and later toured as a performer and photographer with the musical performing arts company "Up with People". Perazza devoted his life to photography, both as an artist and as a teacher. The subjects of his photographs included African-Americans in Detroit, Latinos in Michigan, life in his homeland of Puerto Rico, and police work in Detroit, as he served as a photographer for the Central Photo Unit of the Detroit Police Department for 11 years. His artwork has been exhibited throughout Michigan and around California, Texas, Washington, D.C. and Chicago. He died July 28, 1998.
The Julio Perazza collection includes three series: Visual, Printed, and Audiovisual. The collection offers significant visual documentation to researchers interested in artistic photography, the Detroit Latino community, Detroit Police Department, and the city of Detroit in general. Highlights of the collection include photographs of Latino community cultural events, daily police activities, and Perazza's "Demolished by Neglect" series, a photographic critique of Detroit's urban policies.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Casa de Unidad (Detroit, Mich.); Detroit (Mich.); Detroit (Mich.). Fire Department.; Detroit (Mich.). Police Department.; Fire fighters--Michigan--Detroit.; Hispanic Americans--Education--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Hispanic Americans--Michigan--Detroit.; Perazza, Julio.; Photography--Michigan--Detroit.; Police--Michigan--Detroit.; Puerto Rico.; Students--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; United Farm Workers.; University of Michigan--Students.Students.
Genre Terms:
CDs.; DVDs.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.
- Visual Materials
  The Visual series includes photographic prints and negatives, CDs, and slides. The bulk of the collection consists of photographic negatives and prints taken from the 1970s through the 1990s. Subjects depicted in these photographs include Julio and his family; artistic work, often using models; Puerto Rico; Detroit Police and Fire Departments work and social events; the city of Detroit in general, including buildings, festivals, and people; United Farm Workers events; and the Latino community of Detroit, particularly activities such as various classes (dance, photography, etc.) and social events at Casa de Unidad, which was founded in 1980 to develop, celebrate, and preserve Latino arts and traditions in Southwest Detroit. Some of the photographs were collected by Perazza, including mug shots from the 1930s. Other visual materials include a few photographs on CD and slides of activities at Casa de Unidad, woodworking, and Your Heritage House, a museum and arts center for youth.
  - Photographic negatives
    - 1982
      - Hot Pants Contest (Box 1)
    - June-September, 1984
      - Baker's Keyboard Lounge, June 1984 (Box 1)
      - Ann Arbor Art Fair Street Shoot and Detroit Hispanic Festival, July 1984 (Box 1)
      - Latin American Festival, July 1984 (Box 1)
      - Amigo Band at Chene Park, August 1984 (Box 1)
      - La Casa Detroit Hispanic Salsa, August 1984 (Box 1)
      - La Casa George Vargas Donating his Art Drawing, August 1984 (Box 1)
      - New York Salsa Band Leader Fountain Play, August 1984 (Box 1)
      - Ozzie's Birthday Surprise Party, September 30-31, 1984 (Box 1)
    - March-May 1985
      - Casa de Unidad Creative Writing Class, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Casa de Unidad Dance Class, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Casa de Unidad Graphics-Other, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Casa de Unidad Photo Class, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Funeral at St. Anne Church 1, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Funeral at St. Anne Church 2, March 1985 (Box 1)
      - Bread/Puppet 1, circa April 1985 (Box 1)
      - Bread/Puppet 2, circa April 1985 (Box 1)
      - Arab and Hispanic Dinner, May 1985 (Box 1)
      - Arab/Hispanic Dinner, May 1985 (Box 1)
      - Clark Park-First Time with Photo Class, May 1985 (Box 1)
    - October-December 1985
      - Devil's Night, Christmas, and Carmen/Mark, October-November, 1985S.W.A.P. Wear Red Ribbon, November 1985 (Box 1)
      - S.W.A.P. Ribbon Sign on Casa Door, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Flor y Canto de Navidad B, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Flor y Canto de Navidad C, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Flor y Canto de Navidad D, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Front Room Gallery, Julio Perazza's Photos 1, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Front Room Gallery, Julio Perazza's Photos 2, December 1985 (Box 1)
      - Tree Trimming Party A, December 1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
    - May 1986
      - Theaters A, May 1986 (Box 1)
      - Theaters B, May 1986 (Box 1)
      - Theaters C, May 1986 (Box 1)
      - Theaters D, May 1986 (Box 1)
    - 1990
      - Brooklyn Youth Center Photography Class (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
    - 1991 (Box 1)
    - 1992
      - Grand Prix (Box 1)
    - 1993 (Box 1)
    - 1995 (Box 1)
    - 1996 (Box 1)
    - Demolished by Neglect Series (Box 1)
    - Experimental Media, undated (Box 1)
    - Holy Trinity Church, undated (Box 1)
    - Michigan Catholic News, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1999; undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous, 1978-1999; undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1969-1986; undated (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1970-1983; undated (Box 4)
  - Photographic prints
    - Brooklyn Youth Center Photography Class, 1990 (Box 2)
    - Festivals and Performances, 1985 undated (Box 2)
    - Grand Prix, 1992 (Box 2)
    - Julio Perazza and Family, undated (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1971-1986; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Models, undated (Box 2)
    - Police and Fire, 1934-1994; undated (Box 2)
    - Portraits, Groups, etc., 1976; 1984 undated (Box 2)
    - Puerto Rico, undated; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Students, undated (Box 2)
    - Thanksgiving Day Parade, undated (Box 2)
    - United Farm Workers, undated (Box 2)
  - Large Format Photographic Prints
    - African-American Community, undated (Box 5)
    - Artistic Work, undated (Box 6)
    - Bagley Street Photograph Sale and Farewell Gathering, 1997 (Box 5)
    - City of Detroit, General, undated (Box 6)
    - Diptyches and Triptyches, undated (Box 5)
    - Joint Session with Vito Valdez, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1972 undated (Box 5)
    - Models
      - Cardona, Ana, 1984 (Box 5)
      - Paras, Laura, circa 1984 (Box 5)
      - Perazza, Rachel, circa 1980 (Box 5)
    - Police and Fire, 1995 undated (Box 5)
  - Unidentified images, 1985 undated; 2 optical disks CDs (Box 2)
  - Slides, undated (Box 2)
- Printed
  The Printed series includes materials from a class on photography taught by Perazza at the Brooklyn Youth Center in Detroit; flyers and notices of exhibits on his work; news clippings; materials from Perazza's ofrenda, a celebration of his life and work; and a price list for some of his works.
  - Brooklyn Youth Center Photography Class, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Exhibit Flyers and Notices, 1986; 2004 undated (Box 2)
  - News Clippings, 1999-2004 (Box 2)
  - Ofrenda Exhibit, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Price List, circa 1986 (Box 2)
  - Printed Images and Sketches, undated (Box 2)
- Audiovisual
  The Audiovisual series includes a motion picture, as well as several DVDs, U-matics, and VHS tapes. The motion picture was created by Latino students at the University of Michigan in the early 1970s intended as a recruiting tool to encourage individuals to apply for admission. The DVDs feature interviews, some in Spanish, with Perazza and other members of the Latino community in Detroit, a concert, and drives and walks around the city of Detroit. The U-matics and VHS tapes also feature interviews with members of the Latino community, as well as Perazza's work with social service organizations and a presentation on Rinc?n, Puerto Rico.
  - Motion picture created by Latino students at the University of Michigan in the early, 1970s (Reel 1)
    (16mm, polyester, black and white)
  - Interviews, Concert, Drives and Walks around Detroit, 1985; 3 optical disks DVDs (Box 7)
  - U-matic
    - Rincón, Puerto Rico: A Small Corner of the World, 1981 (Box 7)
    - You...My Sweet/Dreamscape Version '82, 1982 (Box 7)
  - VHS
    - La Casa Street Video Tape 0, circa 1987 (Box 7)
    - La Casa Street Video Tape 4, 1987 (Box 7)
    - LA-SED Summer Youth Program, 1985 (Box 7)